Hello, welcome. It is April 10th, 2025.
We're in active inference math stream
12.1 with Ola running. Going to be
discussing elbowing stein variational
bays with stein mixture inference. So,
thank you for joining. Looking forward
to this presentation and discussion.
Great. Thanks for having me. Um yeah,
I'm all running and presenting the work
I've done together with
Distri Smith and Thomas Hammer on
varational base uh with Stein mixtures.
Um so let's get into
it. So uh this is the plan. We'll talk
about inference and particle based
methods um and particular uh steinbased
methods which came about in 2016. just
go
over uh an overview of what these are to
catch everybody up and then the key
problem with them which is the
underestimate variance as our models get
high
dimensional uh then I'll show shortly uh
shortly about our approach which is d
mixture inference and the new thing here
is introducing
um a neighborhood to each of the
particles we'll talk a little bit about
that and then evidence that this mixture
actually helps with the issue of
dimensionality curse of dimensionality.
And finally, Stein mixture in French is
a
um is
a blackbox inference engine in the
proistic programming language on pyro.
So I'll plug that a little bit at the
end. Yeah. So um just to set the stage
here. So making predictions and sort of
modeling uh systems is ubiquitous. Uh so
the group I'm in works with uh um
structural biology. Uh but I'm looking
to applications in in robotics and
potentially finance as well. And and
sort of at an abstract level, what we're
looking for is a trustworthy systems. We
want something that's accurate when it
meets ex when our data meets our
expectation and uncertain when it's
either surprising, ambiguous, or
missing. So illustrating it here by
where we have a we have a data
generating process dotted line and then
we have a method which is trying to
infer um uh to infer the process. This
is the red line and so we only we only
give it uh sufficient data in the green
regions and what we're looking for is
something that captures the uh the the
the process in the green region and gets
uncertain in this in between region. And
so on the left hand side you would have
something that's accurate but it's uh
but it's overly confident
um because it the uncertainties uh is
collapsed in the in between region and
the right hand side is what we're uh
what we're what we want. So here the
blue region could be any potential curve
um and it's like 95 or 90% HDI. So it's
like the likeliest would be in here.
Good.
Um, yeah. And so just to make it
slightly more concrete, so in
prediction, you might have something
like a overconfident uh overconfident
mobile uh mobile robot. So if you for
example have a uh robot navigating no
terrain, um it will have a sort of
uncertainty about its orientation and uh
uh and position. uh but as you put it
into new terrain for example by removing
a tree you would want this uncertainty
uh to to spread out so that you can
invoke emergency protocols and an over
confident protocol would uh uh sorry
overconfident a robot might lead to
crashes because it's there's a
disambiguity between its actual location
and where it believes it's at. And this
is a this is a we have a talking with
some underwater uh robotics labs and
they say that this is an issue
in one out of€ 250 missions and this can
be quite expensive with robot costing
between
20,000 and 10 million depending on on
the size of the robot for deep sea
robots. another issue. So that was sort
of when we're talking about prediction,
but when we're talking about modeling,
uh uh protein structures, uh
threedimensional protein structures have
uh regions which are sort of conserved,
so they stay um um or ordered, so they
don't fluctuate very much, but it's it's
a it's a molecule interacting with the
solvent around it. uh so the whole thing
will move slightly and then you have
some regions which are unstructured and
highly disordered and they will be
moving around. So if you want a uh a
description of the structure it's not
enough uh of the three-dimensional
structure of the protein. It's not
enough to know just um um sort of an
image of of the structure cuz there's
might be some areas which are not which
will only be very or very unlikely to be
in that particular position. So you want
some sort of a representation which de
uh captures that you have flexibility
within the mod u molecule and
uncertainty is a natural way of
representing this.
Okay. So and and the way we are going to
go about this is with bashian
inference. So just a short reminder uh
of bashian inference. So we're given
observations uh x. So this is things we
get to see and we have a model with some
uh latent parameters unseen parameters
which I'm going to call theta
throughout. And then we can apply base
rule to get to uh take our beliefs uh
prior beliefs about theta and
incorporate uh the observations we're
seeing to get to our
posterior. Uh and we commonly use this
posterior to either we want to sample
from it which is the techniques I'm
going to show you here uh or on some
cases you want to compute expectations
with respect to the
posterior. Now we have two challenges.
This first challenge is key like is
important in terms of what we're doing
here which is our model of data uh is
highdimensional and the other problem uh
which something you work around when
you're doing this type of uh
algorithmics is you don't want to
evaluate the nom length in constant
because it's uh interactable
analytically interactable at
least so uh so so this methodology sort
of first came out uh came about in 2012
and the Key idea is to sort of take a a
simple me uh measure and then find a um
a a push forward sort of deterministic
map such that you transform this very
simple measure into the target measure
and our target measure in in patients
inference setting is is our
posterior and uh so this is one aspect
of it we're trying to find this
deterministic map and uh secondly we're
going to move not the entire density
because that would require us to compute
the normal normalizing constants. We're
only going to be comput uh we're only
going to be moving particles. So we're
going to move something that looks like
samples from this simple distribution
towards target distribution. And so the
uh multi and masuk did this using uh
what was it uh orthogonal polomials. So
like they had this basis of polinomials
and then they found so of one
constructed one function which did the
move the entire
transport. Uh that was in 2012 and then
in 2016 uh Steinverian grad descent came
out. So the way they find that they
determine the transport is they uh they
choose a distance between distribution.
So the simple distribution row and the
target distribution the posterior um and
then you apply your transport and sort
of they uh Kyouong and Dilling did two
things. The first thing was they
deconstructed the transport into an
iterative process
um and secondly they sort of gave a
simple form to each of these transports
which is just a pertubation to um to our
identity
map. Um and then after iterating this
process, they would then make sure that
each iteration you would get closer to
uh uh from the from
the from this sort of simple prior
metric towards the stereo metric and and
that the key result here is that they
get a close form for the sort of finding
this vector field which is making taking
uh giving us the direction of our
transport.
So just taking this apart uh the name
apart we see the stevational gradient
descent. So it's a gradient descent like
uh algorithm we get a update rule which
looks like the classical gradient
descent only our our thetas here are
random variables and not the parameters
as we would be used to and the way it
works is we draw a set of particles from
uh from our prior. this set of particles
we put an empirical measure on um and
then we compute or we find the
minimizing distance uh in terms of scale
uh towards for the next step and we
apply that transport so that uh that
that vector field to the particles
rather than the entire density and this
eventually converges uh to our
target target
density and then there's the stein part
so this is going to get us uh uh get us
the direction in which to move
particles. Um so uh what they find is
they find a direction which is the
maximal decreasing uh direction in the K
in terms of KL uh where the vector field
is contained within a large enough class
of functions called big okay and so uh
this was known before but there's a
relation between uh the kale divergence
when you have this particular form uh of
transport and uh the stein uh well
kernstein discrepancy and so this
kernstein discrepancy is really looking
at an operator operating on the vector
field and it takes this particular form
turns out there are more but this is the
most common but common form and here um
uh we have the score function and then
we have we have our vector field I'm
just because I had questions about this
before we oh this is an old version
sorry uh the score function allows us to
this should be theta down here and then
we don't get to evaluate the we don't
have to evaluate the
um the gradient with respect to the
evidence or sorry the derivative with
respect to to the evidence that will
just be zero. So we can evaluate the
score by just having a joint uh over
theta and x over a lat
observations. And the second insight uh
from that one was sort of well we can
have a a form for the for the for the
vector field but we can actually also
compute it uh if we choose the space
correctly. Uh oh that should be
uh and and what the space of functions
that we're choosing is reproducing
kernel of hbert space uh and where where
our what we get is with a kernel is the
partial evaluation uh is a point in the
hbert space. So if we have a way of uh
if we have uh have kernels available to
us with simple functional forms then we
also have a way of computing uh
computing the optimal direction
um and and Colonel Hilbert spaces or
sorry uh reproducing colonel Hbert
spaces have sort of been studied both in
uh in u in gshian processes and uh and I
think support vector machines before
this. we have quite a
few available. Um the one we're going to
be focusing on here is the squared
exponential kernel. Uh functional form
is given here. Uh there's quite a few
different ones. There's also so these
are scalar kernels and what you do is
you then take identity uh matrix to make
it to into a a vector field over uh over
RD. There's also matrix variants and
then we have operators which allow us to
combine kernels and and there's a lot of
equations here and I sort of this is a
simpler view of the whole thing. So uh
if we we have a kernel and it's it's
partial evaluation gives us a kernel in
the function hbert uh in reproducing
kernel hbert space. So for example a
constant kernel um that just our
constant will decide uh exactly which
value we take. Um in a linear kernel you
would have something like um the kernel
sorry the the the partial evaluation
whichever one we choose will choose the
the the slope of our function and the
key one we'll be working with is the
squared exponential also known as the
gshian and there the partial evaluations
uh give us the mean whereas we have a a
hyperparameter we have to set ourself
which is the bandwidth and that is going
to choose sort of the the width of our
of our caution. C can you just clarify
what the red and the blue are are for
these different kernels?
Yeah. So these are I'm taking a kernel,
right? A kernel is a function in this
case it's just R goes to R goes to R. So
X here is a free variable and and and
and our number is a fixed one of the
parameters. And so uh the blue dotted
line corresponds to fixing one of the
parameters to two. The gray one is
fixing it to one sorry to zero and the
red is fixing it to to 2 minus
2. Is there a reason for two and
negative -2 or is this just showing like
the two directionalities you can take
from zero or is there something about
the two? No, there's nothing particular
about choosing min. It's choosing both
sides of uh when we just have when we
just have a line, right? Uh it was just
to show illustrate sort of what happens
with the only interesting boundary here
which is over zero. Awesome. So they're
like the two directions you can go
updating the kernel.
Yes. if we're in one dimensional
space and then they all have
hyperparameters like a length scale or
uh which I've sort of shown down here
but they also just chosen arbitrarily
just to illustrate uh this functional
view. All right. So uh recall that I
showed you this uh this functional form
of the update just writing it out uh
with expectations. So right now I'm just
applying it to two two particle system
we get a we get something that uh that
behaves like we see this vector field
actually behaves like forces acting on
physical particles. So the first term is
a defractive uh force. It's moving
towards the nearest mode in our
posterior and it's moving each of the
particles like we're taking the it's a
mean field method right so we're taking
the average uh effect uh and moving in
the particle according to that so we
have the effective force in blue and
then we have a repulsive force which
acts pair-wise between particles and
that is keeping the particles apart uh
so they will have uh so they will not
collapse onto uh each other if we only
had the first uh the first term here,
the attractive force, we would have no
benefit of having more than one particle
uh because everything would just
collapse to the
news and then put in our final system.
So we initialize like these positions
randomly. We run this system forward and
what we get is something that looks a
akin to samples from the posterior. They
are not exactly samples which is also
why we call them particles. they have
they have correlation structures which
are sort of different than you would
have MCMC but they do certainly retain
some sort of correlation structure I
don't think it's well characterized
though at the
moment so uh so that sort of gives an
idea
about a particle approach and so uh
particle approaches like in one
dimension these they're shown like they
are as good good as MCMC but as we go up
in dimensionality we start seeing
issues. So yeah, I'm doing the same
system I was doing before. I'm using a
basian neural network which has in the
low dimensions 41 dimensions and the
high 10,100 uh 4001
uh dimension and we we capture some
uncertainty uh in this in between region
when we're using in the load uh uh in
the low uh dimensional system but as we
move up in dimensions this completely
collapses. Now the weather basian
network sort of how many parameters also
decides
um um how expressive our model is and so
uh sort of as you can see with the ideal
you get less expressive like you there's
fewer curves you're actually able to fit
uh with a lower dimensional BN which is
why you see a difference in terms of
uncertainty in the ideal case going from
low to moderate
So
interesting question then is well when
do we sort of stop trusting stein
version of gra descent and uh Jimmy B in
2001 came up with an interesting
experiment where you have um Jian we let
it dimen multivariate gshian let its
dimensionality grow slowly and then
you're looking at so what is the average
uh
empirical variance you get per
dimension of your estimate. And what you
see with dimensional grain descent is
already at five dimensions. You've sort
of have this uh marginal variance. Uh
and so you should really not trust uh
uncertainty estimations if you have a
problem which is five or higher
dimensional and there's a lot of these.
How does that relate to the
factorization? Like the difference
between doing five parameters in a joint
distribution or factorizing some of the
variables apart.
I'm not sure I completely follow
like when you're talking about the
dimensionality increasing this is doing
a joint distribution of all of those
okay in their possible mutual influence.
Yeah. So here we're actually so our um
our multivariate gshian is assumed
completely independent which is why we
can compute this very simply
easily. So it's interesting question
whether how it actually works if you
start having coariances as well but this
experiment is really the simplest
version you could imagine where you just
have a okay and and if there were
covariances do you think that would make
the situation worse or more tractable? I
would assume I I would assume it would
make it worse. Uh this is sort of the
simplest version of the system I could
imagine. Uh so this would make it worse.
So this is sort of a lower bound on what
we're uh what we should
expect. Um
yeah. Yes. Good. So onto our approach
sign inference. So what we uh propose is
to have separate the particle space and
the uh the laten parameter space so that
you get a hierarchical model and you let
the uh the uh the particles move in this
uh in the site uh space and then you let
each particle parameterize uh its own
variational distribution which then
exists in the same space as our
posterior. And so what you get is you
get a mixture approximation of the same
uh operational distribution uh to our
posterior and uh here m is the number of
particles. So it would be two. So if
you're using 10 particles then you're
using a then you would have a a 10
component mixture
approximation and just to motivate it uh
we can rethink sort of we can rethink
the the uh steinber should be descent
particles as sort of the take if you
could imagine taking up gshian and then
letting the variance go to zero you
would get something that's just be a
direct delta function uh distribution
but it would just be like a a a
probabilistic atom. And so you can think
of in this sense you could think of sort
of a stein particle as just the mu
location of this sort of degenerate
caution. And so going in the opposite
direction, you could say well uh if we
then uh allow the variance uh of of the
of the normal to also be represented by
the particle then each particle now
becomes two-dimensional.
um and and and and summarizes this
caution. So so we this our particles now
both have a location but they also have
a component for the variance. Um and
then with multiple uh like having many
of these particles you would suddenly
get a mixture approximation and in this
case a gshian mixture approximation. And
so our goal now is to be able to move
these particles uh in the in in um in
such a way that we're sort of minimizing
a distance to the uh to the posterior to
get a uh version of base
method. And to do this we we're going to
look back to sort of meanfield version
of inference and just go here. You have
a you have a simple parametric
distribution. So we not we're not
necessarily trying to hit fix uh hit uh
get the shape right of our posterior.
However, we are going to work with
something that's of uh that is
tractable. And so uh here you just a
gshion summarized by this this midline
its mean and we sort of then move the
mean such that it's covering as well as
it can uh the posterior
distribution and we'll do this with a
proxy distance. Um so it will not be the
kale we're minimizing anymore. It will
be evidence lower bound.
And so just to recall that as well, it's
it's our evidence lower bound is just
the difference between the our evidence
of yeah log probability of our data and
the K between our approximate uh
distribution Q and our true posterior
and it's and it's this expression and
the reason we work with this is this
this expression here which compute
especially if we have a very simple
rational distribution Q we might even be
able compute the the differential
entropy
analytically. Good. So the idea of uh so
as I mentioned we were going to take uh
our particles and give them a
neighborhood. So in terms of of uh of
the equation I was showing you before,
we could think of making these uh the
parameters uh of our rational
distribution, we could make those into
random
variables. And if we do that then uh we
would get a and we had multiple of them
then we have a uh we would have an
empirical measure on uh on the
parameters of our of our rational
distributions and it would be the same
as replacing the score function the
stein version of gradient descent uh
with with some sort of uh of loss
function here which is going to be
similar to an elbow.
Now we'll have to do a bit of massaging
to make sure that this is still a valid
uh meth methodology. But sort of in its
sort of simplest form, this is all we're
doing. We're we are moving taking our
transport. We are moving on these
particles which are now a hierarchy
higher than it was before and we are
moving them using uh using this uh this
elbow formulation instead uh of of in
terms of the of the score
function and the m uh the evidence lower
bound that we're using is takes this
particular form. You could use simpler
versions of this but it actually it
behaves doesn't behave well. uh so we
need to take in particular we need to
take this uh the differential entropy in
terms of uh of our rational
approximation not just each of the
terms.
Um in order to show that this is correct
we do have a constraint on this which is
our guide distribution operational uh uh
distribution Q that needs to be the same
uh for every single particle. In other
words, our our our function our function
of row uh needs to be symmetric. So it
can't depend on the ordering in which
you uh in which you uh parameterize
it. With this change uh we can use uh an
extension of time gradient descent
called nonlinear stevial gradient
descent. And what this is again dealing
on le what they did was they replaced so
it's dime version of B descent we're
minimizing the KL divergence uh and what
this extension does it allows us to
minimize um functionals of our initial
distribution row uh with our uh
differential entropy as our as a
regularizer and what that is doing is in
of ensuring uniformity so ensuring that
our our density row gets spread out
there's some prerequisites for this.
First of all, as I already mentioned, uh
our functional when uh parameterized by
uh by empirical measure needs to be
symmetric. Secondly, we need to have a
differential evaluation
map. Oh, this is again the old version.
I'm sorry. This should be this is all
the way up to M. There's nothing special
about M here. Um but we need to be able
to to to evaluate uh the functional
given our particles and using an
empirical measure that's trivial. It's
just evaluating at each of the each of
the points and finally we have this
regularizing term which is ensuring that
our particles are spread
out. So our uh as we show okay but this
is uh we have an instance of nonlinear
stress gradient descent uh first of all
it fulfills that the particle
approximation is symmetric because we
chose the same que for each of our each
of our articles so the same uh guide we
have a differentiable map but it's
trivial to evaluate on the empirical
measure and if we choose it needs to be
differentiable so we also choose the uh
our guide to be differentiable and
finally Finally uh we were when I showed
you we were replacing sort of the inner
part of the of the vector field by EV
evidence lower bound but recall we're
now this is the objective we're actually
optimizing is the this functional uh
plus some entry picture in Monroe which
is up here and so we need to show that
that is also an evidence lower bound in
order to have a valid version uh
approach and if you choose so they have
this alpha parameter if reduce that to
one and you look at the population
limit. So like infinitely many particles
and I'm moving this um then we actually
we can actually show that this is the
case. So it's a valid fractional base uh
method. And so if you revisit the
experiment I was showing you in the
beginning um with uh within version
gradient descent we had collapse. And
now with our stein mixtures we see that
we're going up in dimensionality our
particles
uh are in in theta space. So in the some
posterior space uh our particle we now
have uncertaintity estimation in this uh
in the moderate dimensional case as
well. However, it's not uh it's not
ideal yet. Uh we are here we're using
five particles and so you can get better
approximations using more but the cost
of the sort of the cost of each step is
uh quadratic in the number of particles.
So you want to use as few particles as
possible. Um but but there's so there's
there's still room to uh for
improvement. Uh but but we are sort
of work it works better than than uh
than steep for this uh uncertainty
estimation. So as I said we we we sort
of there's still improvements to be
made. There's some key design dimensions
that we can address. crystal dynamic
stability which is we sort of stress
gradient descent has been understood as
sort of gradient flow in
uh in in the space of distributions.
However, if you just tune that naively
with mixture models then you might move
your gradient flow might move somewhere
which is no longer a mixture model. So
we in order to sort of analyze and
understand uh
uh sty mixture inference you need some
some new theory there. Uh but with this
if you get this gradient uh flow
uh if you nail that then you start being
able to do things like you can you can
choose hyperparameters by choosing
different formulations of the gradient
flow. uh and and and for example look at
uh time flow versus uh this is getting
to technology sorry uh um what you can
do you can start uh determining
something like kernels based on having
uh this type of formulation it also
allows us to tell things about how fast
it converges which is currently not
known uh the result on stress gra
descent at IC law this year which shows
that it's in KSD it's actually as good
as
uh as uh MCMC. So that's very good in
terms of KST. Then there's kernel design
like actually choosing the the the
kernel. So one way to do this is knowing
what the actual uh dynamics are. uh but
also then understanding based on which
kernel you choose how does this uh uh
affect dynamic stability and Duncan has
an interesting paper on that uh for ste
which I believe can also lift to time
mixtures finally there's accelerating
acceleration options like Newton methods
preconditioning gradient flows to
completely avoid uh computing uh
kernels Yeah. So that's sort of a rough
outline of ST mixture inference. Uh it's
available in numpyro. So deep
probabilistic programming language. Uh
it separates model from uh inference. It
has a
DSL for probabilistic programs embedded
in Python. So you can have arbitrary
Python in between random sites. It uses
non-standard
interpretation. And most importantly
like for this talk I guess is that Stein
mixture is a blackbox. uh inference
engine in the
system. Um, of course, we need to be
able to take derivatives, hardware,
acceleration, linearity, and all that is
handed off to Jax. So, to just build the
layer on top of
Jax. Yeah, there's been a lot of people
involved in this. So first of all the
Pyrus devs that helped me build the the
um the inference engine Martin and
Koviaak and Eupong and Akmmed was who
did the first version of it uh which
then evolved into our um into our
uh uh the current version of Steinvi
which is the name of the inference
engine and then my co-authors so my list
who first formulated this problem when
he was at PhD with Patrick Smith and
then Thomas Hammer who's my PI um has
worked with B for the last couple of
years and Christoff Li who's an expert
in Stein's method at University of
Luxembourg the key
references sum up so if the introduction
into this approach to Bashian inference
uh is the first one then there's the two
Stein papers uh from 2006 16 and 19 and
then our uh my paper here which is going
to be at IC law this year. Yeah, this
the inference group and uh yeah at KU
and yeah yeah
thanks. Awesome. Thank you. All right,
I'll ask a few questions and then if
anyone watching along wants to ask a
question, I'd be happy to. So to kind of
pull back and
resummarize, what makes KL divergence
optimization for particle transport
plausible where distributional transport
is not
plausible? Uh so the the key issue here
is computing the normalizing constant.
You need you need to be able to
renormalize
uh uh reormalize the density. So
like if you choose a very nice base of
functions such as so they were using
this orthogonal uh uh polomial basis
then you you can do it but it restricts
sort of how expressive you are able to
do uh be in terms of what you're
transporting a particle methods you so
you it scales proportional with the
number of particles so it's cheap to
compute
Great. So you you mentioned that the
compute is quadratic in the particle
number. So what are the computational
complexity considerations for this
method? And then h how does that even
kind of qualitatively relate to the MCMC
approach? like if that's giving a better
posterior estimate of the real paths,
what are the conditions where MCMC is
just straightforwardly a better method
to use versus exploring how many
particles etc for this method?
So uh so first in terms of MCMC I was
like in a toy example you would probably
just use MCMC but it becomes truly
intractable if you sort of if it's the
issue if especially if you're using HMC
or something like this is that it's
becomes it you need to work on all data
points right so because you need to
compute the grade like when you're doing
a simplex integration you need to
compute at every step you need to
compute the gradient with respect to
every data point and That's why MCMC
just doesn't that doesn't scale to the
type of data uh data sets that we're
sort of interested in. um in terms of
how is the complexity with um compared
between Steinver descent and SMI the key
uh sort of the expensive part is
computing the kernel you need to compute
the pair-wise components this is why
it's n squ and we have the same kernel
structure uh for uh SVD and smi though
the difference here is that we can what
you can do uh with five particles uh
with stein mixtures you might not at all
be able to do on conventional hardware
uh with the Stein version uh version of
grid descent if your problem is high
dimensional
enough. Okay, so from
the live chat so first quick question
from Gary wrote what language are you
using? So you mentioned the software
package just could you redescribe or
maybe even show the software package or
what programming language is it in and
what is that domain specific language
look like?
Okay. Uh yeah sure. Uh it's so the first
of all the language is in Python
uh and it's um maybe should I share
something else? Yeah, sure.
One second. See if I
have something lying about we can look
at and show
you. All right. Uh, one
second. Ah, here we go.
[Music]
Okay. Yep.
So, can you see it? Yep. It's a little
small. If you could zoom in, but we see
it. Bending the smooth.
Uh okay. Well, I have to do like this.
Uh we can see it. All right. Good. So,
this is a this is
a a via soal uh uh autoenccoder, right?
So, what you're doing is you're taking
you have you have a you have a a guide
which takes uh a picture something uh
down to something uh some to some
lowdimensional model. So we call this
the uh the the encoder and then we have
a model which takes our latent low
dimensional and back to text. Okay. And
so what I'm showing you here is uh is
the the the decoder. So what takes our
latent representation and moving us back
into the original uh uh original space.
So you can think of this as compression
maybe uh if you like. Um okay. And
so
see this is what the random sites look
like. So you have you have a random
variable here. Uh we're going to be
we're going to be using
um a non-standard interpretation. So
like have some have a set of uh
operators which operate on these sample
sites or handlers which operate on these
sample sites and make them behave
differently than otherwise just straight
executing Python. So here I have a
random sample site it's over angles it's
distributed according to a sign by
variant on myis distribution. So it's
just a normal like think of it as a
normal on a Taurus. uh it has some
parameters and then uh I get to uh I
have some observations. So this is like
conditioning same as conditioning on
these angles that I've observed.
Now these uh parameters for my sign
graises I have some location some
concentration these come in this case
from applying uh a neural network or
bashian neural network it's a uh um and
and that's just coded up in flax. So
that's just straight up standard uh
bashian uh sort of uh you know network
and then we sort of we can we can uh
make it into a bash network by just
introducing a prior over its uh over its
uh over the weight. So this is what's
happening here. We're making a bash
neural network. We're saying we have a
uh a recurrent neural network. Uh it's a
random site called decoder. So we can
apply our handlers uh to this site. Uh
and then uh yeah this this just makes
sure that uh it's the right the par like
the right parameters are being updated
when we're doing our uh updates. Okay.
So and that then uh given some some
latent remember they said uh they gave
us my some representation which I can
then map into the parameters my sign on
my system. So this just give you an idea
about this is what the like what
modeling looks like. we introduce uh
random sites and we can do sort of
arbitrary things in Python in between
our random
sites to manipulate whatever uh uh
samples we have. That's the sort of the
the one side of it and then when you
then want to do inference well
you're so we're setting up our inference
method. So right now I'm just testing
thing out. So it's just mean field
operational inference. I have the model
which is what I just showed you. I have
a corresponding guide. So this is my Q I
was talking about. This is the thing
encoding my uh my space into this latent
representation. I'm going to decide uh
on the type of optimizer using Adam and
then I'm saying I'm going to use uh uh
just a standard uh evidence lower bound
here.
um index or numpy where we need to be
explicit about our the state of random
keys. That's what's going on here. And
then I'm running my inference. So now
I'm conditioning uh my uh the
parameters the uh the parameters of the
guide on the observations that I have
available which are stored in fine
site and from there I just dump the
object and I have a separate thing which
does my diagnostics. So I can get my
predictive distribution out. I can see
what does the Ramosandon plot look like.
uh if I want to look at uh histograms of
uh parameters, I can get those out uh
from my predictive. So that's sort of
the the high scale view of a typical
implementation of logic
in awesome. Okay, next question in the
chat. Bert Burkers
wrote in the slide showing attraction
and repulsion there are two particles
with vectors pointing in many
directions. How should one interpret
these directions and their angles?
Should I?
Yes, this better. Perfect. Good. Okay.
So the uh the blue uh the blue arrow
will always point towards the closest uh
mean. So
it's we're looking at a gshian
distribution here and it just in a
mobile right. So the the particles are
just the closest mean will always be the
center of the
crux. Um so that's what the blue arrows
uh are uh are showing you. And then the
the if you aligned up uh the red arrows
there are the forces acting on the
particles by each other. And so they
will all in a two system uh particle
system they will always be plus and
minus at least if you
choose gshian kernel of the same
expression. So they will be of the same
magnitude. You have three particles it
becomes more complex. And then the black
and I should have mentioned this that
that's the net effect of the two. Okay,
so it's looking at when you add up these
two uh these two components, then you
get the net effect of the black uh the
black
arrow. So that's when you're then taking
a step, you're moving in the direction
of the black arrow and then like
depending on how you choose your
epsilon, you might not take the full
length of this uh uh of the of the
course be some epsilon size of it. And
just to kind of clarify, what tunes the
relative strength of the attractive and
the repulsive force? Like at the end of
all of this procedure, how do you ensure
that you haven't over or underestimated
the variance envelope?
Okay. So this particle like this system
of equations will when we are at
convergence this will there will be no
force acting on any of
them right and so this this this
equation will be
zero. Got it? So the
particles engage in these attractive
repulsive physics-like interactions
amongst observations
delta-like kind of hidden Gaussian
observations that can be variance
reinflated and that
particle transported particle
distribution. It's almost like
recapitulating what the MC would give
you from samples because you do want to
sample from a posterior distribution
with a finite number of spikes. And
instead of actually just doing that
gradient calculation at the data point
level as done in MC here, you're
learning these transport functions with
certain conditions that lets you move
the distribution project down to
particles and reinflate the particles
back in your contribution to this
mixture model.
Yeah.
We're we're moving the particles so that
they get towards the posterior. So like
the data is all our observations are
hidden in in terms in in steambridge in
descent at least in in in our score
right
okay I guess just taking one step back
and then if anybody else wants to write
any questions how did you come to this
problem for your posttock like what led
you through studies and everything to
want to target this
uh Yeah. So, yeah. So, actually it was
uh it was
uh it was uh Akmed who so we my original
P my PhD was on sort of trying to find
uh to determine threedimensional
structure of proteins given
um given the sequence or the pro uh
protein uh 3D structure bro and and when
I when I started
um we had Alpha come out sort of two
months after um which made the which and
what that sort of that was declared as a
solution to the problem which made it uh
a a bit of an interesting uh situation
to be in but uh but Akmat had started
working on this um cuz he thought it
mapped well onto sort of so one thing we
want right is we want to be able to
uh with our with the
probabilistic deep probabilistic pro uh
program is we want to automate uh
automate inference and we sort of we
know
that there like this can't be done
entirely but we want something that's
very expressive and cheap to compute
with and and it's version of gradient
descent has had these two attractive
properties it's very cheap and easy to
understand uh and it's
cheap to compute with. So we sort of we
built a stress descent uh inference
engine and then we were looking at well
we have this issue uh and we wanted to
apply it to proteins uh eventually and
so what I was showing you before is well
now I'm getting to that phase because it
turned out to be a lot harder than we
first expected to actually like getting
the inference engine running was not as
much work and as then finding out is
this thing correct? Uh, and that's that
what we spent the next while on couple
of years.
There's always a funny postto story. Um,
what does it look like to go from the
open- source code that you have to
adapting it to a problem? Like what's
the kind of recipe that somebody would
take from from um that's one question.
And then a second question, however you
want to do this, is where do you see
this method in terms of the landscape of
like generative
AI, pure neural network based
approaches, etc.
Take the first one uh first. So what we
would do there is we would go
uh and okay so we would import our
method instead of uh instead of uh
instead of SVI and then we would replace
it
here. And now of course we need to
choose a kernel. So the RBF
kernel that that's it. Okay. Just just
to confirm that move because it's
largely built upon the JS Pyro approach.
It's not so different than just flipping
an import for a model that's already
written within that way.
Yeah.
Okay. So, how about how how does
somebody even if this is sort of a a
basic question for pyro users? Let's say
somebody's looking at, you know, the
temperature and the humidity in a room
and making a kind of active inference
model where they're going to run a
heater or a cooler or some other kind
of, you know, how do we go from just the
observables and the unobservables of our
target system of interest into
representing it in a way that allows it
to be inferred using this probabilistic
approach.
Yeah. So, so what you're describing
sounds like the sort of the basian
network or factor graph uh right and
that's the model I was showing you is
how I write that off. So I like whenever
I have a random variable and in this
case this is not the greatest of
examples to look at but uh but I guess I
have a set right so I have a random
variable here which is my latent and
then I'm saying that that there's an
arrow between said and and uh and my my
angles right and that's the same as
saying like I have two uh I have a graph
actually I can show you instead of
telling
Um let's see. So this is the sort of
view that I think you were thinking of
like we have random variables uh uh sort
of here we have set and we have another
one which is observed is angle but
that's just that's just described as a
python function which is model which is
using these special uh specialized um
uh like uh effectful uh methods one of
them being sample and another one being
what and a sample corresponds to to to a
circle Here uh plate corresponds to what
you would know in plate in a vation
graph and then uh we have
deterministics. So these are these uh
dotted line circles.
Awesome. And is this generated or
specified in another file in this repo?
How the bve model? Yeah. Yeah. That's so
that's just the so the thing I was
showing you at first this model is just
that it's specifying this thing and it's
just written as a function and that
function I then act on with uh with my
particular inference engine.
Awesome. Okay. So then kind of again
pulling back like where do you see these
methods in the toolkit of what people
could do with with pure neural network
approaches or transformer-based
approaches today?
So uh like so I mean so the Bashian
neural network is sort of lifting this
up right and like pretending that we can
actually get access to a to the
posterior of its parameters instead of
point estimates and and there are I
think I like the idea of vision neural
networks because exactly because they
sort of at least seems like they could
give us an idea about risk or
uncertainty. There's couple of problems
with it, right? Like it's we have like
moving you have you have two networks
which look different in terms of weight
but represent the same function. So like
whether we are actually whether basian
networks are actually like
uh whether we when we're moving in
weight space whether we're actually
getting different sort of samples even
though we're changing uh changing our
weights is not clear and so so so it's
not really you can't really determine
whether you get different uh different
uh if you running something like epmc
you wouldn't actually know that your
particular
samples or different networks
necessarily. So like estimating how well
you've done or even determining
convergence becomes very hard. Uh but it
does handle sort of misspecification
quite well right like if if you have
something that's exceedingly flexible
you probably have the right model in
there. So that's why I think basin
networks are attractive but we need to
address this non identifiability
eventually and I might be able to do
that with kernels but we don't know yet.
We have some ideas.
Cool. Well, is there anything else you
want to show or add or like how can
people other than reading the paper and
checking out the repo learn more?
Uh yeah, I mean there's
[Music]
a
sorry this is where you get
started. So pyro.ai take a look. uh our
version is the nonpyro version but pyro
is uh also very uh large and uh very
fully fledged uh deep probabilistic
programming language which I highly
encourage you to take a look at.
Cool. Anything else you want to add?
Okay, awesome. Thank you again Ola for
joining. Super interesting. I I hope we
can continue to learn and that people in
the institute community explore like
pyro methods, RX and fur and we can
start to see where these different
methods complement each other, top
differences, all
that. Cool. Thank you. Bye. Bye.